<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>#!/bin/bash it 'till it works - food</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/feeds/food.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://cannoncontraption.github.io/</id><updated>2023-01-10T23:50:00-05:00</updated><subtitle>The blog of a Zsh user.</subtitle><entry><title>Now You're Cooking with... Cast Iron!</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/castiron.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-10T23:50:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-10T23:50:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2023-01-10:/castiron.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to kick off the new year with an article that I've been meaning to write for a long time now. Unfortunately I seem to have missed the holidays entirely, so this will be too late to give you any tips for entertaining over the holidays …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to kick off the new year with an article that I've been meaning to write for a long time now. Unfortunately I seem to have missed the holidays entirely, so this will be too late to give you any tips for entertaining over the holidays this year. Maybe you'll find this information useful for next year, or some time in between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several months ago, I went camping with some friends at one of the state parks in the area. I was in charge of coming up with meals for the trip, and in charge of cooking them. One of the tools that I've come to absolutely love for this purpose is a dutch oven. The real draw for me (at least at first) was that everything you could make in a crock pot could be brought to a dutch oven with very few modifications, if any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I planned to make a mac-n-cheese and a chili while we were on the trip, and I planned to make the chili overnight in the embers of the camp fire. Both of these wound up going over very well, but there were a few issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the trip, I had borrowed my parents' old enameled dutch oven, which isn't in super great shape, but wasn't something I was interested in damaging further, so I was pretty ginger with it. It never saw any direct flame. While I did put some embers on top, they were cooler embers, almost completely burned out, with a layer of sand between them and the raw enamel surface. I can (somewhat proudly) say that I didn't damage the enamel any further by doing this, though I won't lie, my hands were shaking pretty much the whole time I was doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was using the dutch oven to make chili, I started researching what I should get for my own dutch oven that I could take camping. I ran across a lot of people saying the tool for the job (chili excluded, unfortunately) was bare cast iron. The enamel coating was a liability at high temperatures, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took the usual set of camping supplies on loan from my parents, and one of those supplies was a very small cast iron pan. The food it made was &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; top-notch, but cleaning it was a huge chore, so it only helped make a meal or two at most. At this point I was treating cast iron like a special-occasions-only tool, just because of the extra work it took to clean. However, one major upside to cast iron was that it could be exposed directly to the camp fire without any real risk of permanent damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;...whoops.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months back, one of the friends who came with me on the trip got me a cast iron dutch oven as a birthday present. So, eager to try it out, I immediately made a chili in it! I cooked it overnight to steep the flavors really well, with my usual tomato base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who knows cast iron will know why this was a mistake, but it turned out great, and the pot isn't damaged in the slightest from the encounter. Sure, the factory seasoning was slightly damaged from the acidity in the tomatoes, you could see the line where the chili had been, but it wasn't totally destroyed. I was really impressed with it, since my experience had been a sticky mess every time. This was easy to clean. Even so, it was clear the tomatoes had reacted with the seasoning, so following the instructions that came with the pot, I set out to season it afresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Manufacturer Lies, Community Wisdom&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't follow the tag that comes with your cast iron, folks. This was mistake number 2. Again, to be clear, it still didn't actually make any difference in the end, but I learned a lot about how to care for cast iron this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pot came out sticky, but very well coated. I figured this was normal at first, and so I just spread a thin layer of fresh oil on the surface of the freshly baked seasoning and kept going. Frankly, this worked just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I quickly realized that that sticky texture isn't supposed to be there. Digging around on the internet, I found a lot of (often conflicting) information about the best way to season cast iron, but there are a few things that most people seem to agree on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a vegetable oil or grapeseed oil. Olive oil is OK, but not ideal for a variety of reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coat the surface of the cookware with a &lt;em&gt;very thin&lt;/em&gt; layer of oil, dry it off to be sure it's thin enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bake the cookware &lt;strong&gt;at the smoke point of the oil&lt;/strong&gt; for about an hour, it's important you know what &lt;em&gt;your oil&lt;/em&gt; needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the cast iron cool very slowly to lessen the damage that might come from thermal stresses, this is about the only thing that can actually make cast iron go bad for good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do this for several coats, anywhere between 3-6. Use your judgment for when it's done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the surface of the cast iron is sticky, either you didn't have the oven on high enough, or you applied too much oil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do this on the stove, but you'll need to be attentive 100% of the time, and you'll want to do it at a lower temperature than you feel is right. You can burn off the seasoning by accident this way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;None of this matters 99% of the time, just keep using it until you run into a major problem and you're fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer of my dutch oven basically boiled this down to 'spread vegetable oil over the iron, then bake it for an hour at 300 degrees F,' which is both oversimplified, and wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want better advice from someone with more experience, check &lt;a href="https://www.americastestkitchen.com/articles/3615-how-to-clean-and-season-cast-iron-skillets"&gt;this article on America's Test Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;. It's titled &lt;em&gt;What I Know About Cleaning and Seasoning Cast-Iron Skillets&lt;/em&gt; by Lisa McManus, in case the link goes dead at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What It's Like to Use&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say, the reason I bothered learning any of this is because of how forgiving the dutch oven was. I screwed up pretty majorly when it came to care of the pot, but the chili I made with it was wonderful, it's still in good shape, and I've personally made many more really good meals with it since then. The surface is still almost as nonstick as Teflon, and it's just using some olive oil as a seasoning. I never fixed my mistake with the original coat of oil, either. It's still got a sticky surface in some places, and that just doesn't matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because cast iron holds heat very well, and because it's thick, you can get things cooked well at an overall lower temperature, and the food stays hot for longer once the stove is turned off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was already used to non-stick cookware, and the rules are similar, but slightly different. Cast iron works great with metal utensils, you're not going to damage it or make it badly sticky just by using a fork on it or a metal turner. Just like with nonstick, you want to avoid anything that's too acidic, since it can break down the seasoning. Also just like nonstick, you want to add just a little oil to begin with. You can use both cast iron and nonstick pots and pans without any oil if you're feeling brave, neither should be a significant chore to clean, but your pan will last longer in the case of nonstick, and your seasoning will last longer with cast iron. Cast iron isn't as slippery as nonstick. You'll occasionally see some stuff stick to it, but on the whole it shouldn't be that much harder to clean, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people will tell you not to use any soap at all on cast iron, but you're not really running any risk of damaging anything if you do it occasionally, so long as you aren't using too much. I've heard rumors that the advice to avoid soap is from a pre-detergent era. Older soaps could actually damage cookware, but newer ones are much gentler and should be fine for the most part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line though is not to worry about it. You won't destroy a cast iron pan unless you thermal shock it pretty hard, the worst you're likely to get by ignoring all of what people tell you to do is a sticky pan and maybe a metallic taste in some of your food. If you get the taste, don't worry, so long as you aren't eating your pan, it's non-toxic. That's another advantage over nonstick. Restoring a neglected or damaged pan is really, really easy. I managed to not screw it up too badly (if at all) my first try, in fact, while I've done better in some cases than others, I've done a lot of successful restorations by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;My Journey to Restore My Parents' Pans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to dig out my parents' old pans. None of them had been used in a very long time, with the exception of the one in the camping supplies. Except for that pan, they were all rusty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that this isn't really a problem, not even rust destroys these things. I found a (quite tiny, #3) pan that was rusty. A quick cleaning and seasoning later, and it's been working great for frying sandwich-size eggs, or frying an egg into a kaiser roll or an English muffin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one from the camping supplies, as it turns out, just had a lot of carbon buildup. I scrubbed it all off and then gave it a single coat of fresh seasoning in the oven, and it's as good as new now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little bit later, my mom found another pan in the camping supplies, and this one I documented. It was the worst one I had seen, by far. Here's what it looks like &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="fresh out of the oven shot" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/castiron/seasoned.jpg" width="300px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did just apply a few fresh coats of seasoning, so that's fresh out of the oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came out of the camping supplies, however, it looked much, much worse. I forgot to grab a shot of it dry before I started soaking it in vinegar and water to remove the rust, but here's a picture with the vinegar and water already in place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="fresh out of the camping supplies shot" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/castiron/rusty.jpg" width="300px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And once I had removed the rust:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="fresh out of the rust removal process" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/castiron/bare.jpg" width="300px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now back to the present day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="fresh out of the oven shot" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/castiron/seasoned.jpg" width="300px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, I opted to start with 4 coats of seasoning at first, but in the past few weeks I've been noticing that some things, like vegetables, have started to stick a little bit, so I just gave it another 3 coats. It was just fine for the 4 months in between, however, and that's from halfway to stripped bare. When I said you can't really ruin these things, I meant it. Beyond just being damaged, this one was also pretty old. I asked my mom how long she's had that pan, and for all she knows it's older than she is. We have no idea who originally bought this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Should You Use Cast Iron?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes! I'm surprised I hadn't looked into this sooner, but my negative experiences with cast iron in the past were &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; from improper care and neglect compounding together. Some of the best food I've ever made has been in cast iron, including the best burgers I've ever made. That was over a 3-stone open flame in a fire bowl in the back yard when I was in high school, and while the pan wasn't really properly seasoned then, either, those burgers really were excellent, and if I can ever make them again, I'll definitely post about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cast iron is quite low maintenance, it's non-stick, it's sturdy, and it holds its temperature, leading to less temperature swings on an electric stove. It's also compatible with induction burners, as a bonus. It's not expensive, either. If you look for a pan from Lodge, for example, you're unlikely to need more than $50 for some of the biggest pans. All of my family's cast iron is Lodge at the moment, and all of it performs great. Most of it is older, but the newer stuff is cost competitive with aluminum nonstick, I checked. When you factor in the fact that nonstick pans usually only last 2-5 years, even if you're only concerned about cost, cast iron makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to go make a pizza now, I'll paste in a picture before I post. That pan looks nice, but it's missing the food!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cast iron pizza" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/castiron/pizza.jpg" width="300px"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="food"></category><category term="castiron"></category><category term="cookware"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>Quick Mac and Cheese</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/macncheese.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-29T23:59:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-29T23:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2022-08-29:/macncheese.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So a quick recipe for mac and cheese:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stick of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;gt;1lb shredded cheese (your choice, mix and match to taste)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12-16 oz pasta (Macaroni or shells are best)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double the amount of water (by volume) as pasta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4-1/2 cup milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Instructions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boil water on the stove …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So a quick recipe for mac and cheese:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stick of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;gt;1lb shredded cheese (your choice, mix and match to taste)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12-16 oz pasta (Macaroni or shells are best)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double the amount of water (by volume) as pasta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4-1/2 cup milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Instructions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boil water on the stove on high heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the pasta to the boiling water and cook to taste. I prefer thoroughly soft, though if you like al dente, that's fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the pasta is done, strain out the water. You can use a strainer or a spoon and a steady hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn the stove down to low heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the butter, allow to melt fully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the butter is melted, you can switch the stove off. Don't remove the pan yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slowly add the cheese to the pasta until the cheese covers every noodle. It should have a decent, thick consistency. Once you've added all of the cheese, add the milk and stir completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The macaroni is ready to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I served this while camping recently, and it went over really well. Like I mentioned in the &lt;a href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/food.html"&gt;food intro&lt;/a&gt; I'm just a guy who likes to cook, so I honestly didn't find this anywhere online, it was mostly just a guess from having done it to a recipe before. The main pitfall I've found with other off-the-shelf macaroni and cheese recipes is that they don't usually call for enough cheese, so my biggest recommendation is to use double what most other recipes call for, you'll thank me for it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Food"></category><category term="food"></category></entry><entry><title>An Instant Pot is NOT a Slow Cooker!</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/an-instant-pot-is-not-a-slow-cooker.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2019-05-14:/an-instant-pot-is-not-a-slow-cooker.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine for a moment a world where you need to bring food with you every day. I know, I know, no one reading this could possibly be in that situation. But bear with me anyhow. Let's just assume for a moment that you have a nice chili that you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine for a moment a world where you need to bring food with you every day. I know, I know, no one reading this could possibly be in that situation. But bear with me anyhow. Let's just assume for a moment that you have a nice chili that you want to slow cook- you put all the ingredients in your crock pot, and since obviously everyone in this situation only owns a crock pot (college student times, it really happened) you put your rice in with everything else. You turn it on, next morning everything comes out well enough- the rice may be a bit soggy but you live with it since it's got a good taste and the flavors blend nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a bit. Rather than having a crock pot, the crock pot started flaking off rust chips because it's old (also happened) and it's now gone. In its place is a shiny new instant pot! When I was in this situation, I figured they couldn't be too different and just put my usual chili recipe in there and turned on the pressure. Boy was I in for a shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How not to cook rice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instant pot over and over again displayed the error "BURN". It didn't seem to matter what settings I used to make this happen, or whether it was the whole thing at once as before, or just the rice on its own with the "rice" setting advertised on the front. Every time it would display this message, and there'd be a sticky mess of rice remains stuck to the bottom of the pot, sometimes with other ingredients trapped underneath. All in all, not a pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Instant Pots are NOT Slow Cookers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My immediate next thought was that the pressure was the problem. The next time I went to cook my chili, I simply set the instant pot on slow cook mode and walked away. All indications were that this would work fine. Then I decided enough time had passed and checked on it. I had set the instant pot to slow cook medium heat, which I figured would probably land somewhere in between low and high on a traditional slow cooker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was wrong. Sticking my finger into a pot of what was essentially still luke-warm soup was not a pleasant surprise. At that point I was about ready to call it quits on that idea, and switched to pressure cook mode. I encountered the same "BURN" error as before, but after a couple of attempts at least I had something I could eat for lunch that week. Trying it again the next week yielded the same result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who might end up in the same sort of position as me, here's about where the Instant Pot's slow cook temperature lines up with a crock pot:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;table border=1px&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Instant Pot setting&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Crock Pot analog&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;High&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Low with the lid off&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Medium&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Keep Warm&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Low&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Off&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Clearly you're not going to get very good results if you go into this without this knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Potential Issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of theories as to why this problem is as bad as it is. Firstly, the lid doesn't seal the same way. The crock pot is designed with a lid that forms a loose seal from the steam built up as the food cooks. While it's not a hard seal, and steam can still escape, there should be no holes in the lid of a properly functioning crock pot, or else the food won't cook right. The Instant Pot's lid is designed for pressure cooking, so it requires pressure to seal completely. This allows for the pressure release and for the lid to come off safely when used as a pressure cooker. There don't seem to be any good third-party lid options, at least none that I tried did the trick. You may have better luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Instant Pot only seems to heat from the bottom, where the crock pot heats all sides. Furthermore, the crock in a crock pot has a fair amount of thermal mass, which helps to spread out the heat. The Instant Pot uses a steel liner, much like a soup pot or a really big saucepan. The Instant Pot may also just not have good enough heat control to give a good in-between heating setting. A lot of steam is required for pressure, which requires a lot of heat. When that kind of heat isn't required, the thermal controls may not be accurate enough to produce a desirable result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back to a real Crock-Pot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, fed up with the extra work being put into lunch for the week, I broke down and bought a crock pot. Immediately I could tell the difference. Like any new appliance, it took some getting used to since the old one did not behave &lt;i&gt;quite&lt;/i&gt; exactly like the old one, but with not very much time I was back to my old routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of this actually happened months ago by now. In fact, this whole blog site just got a minor facelift recently, including new background graphics and some under-the-hood improvements to themeing which made a color change practical. The reason those changes didn't go live in December of last year is because I was planning out this post. Since then, I've had some more time to experiment and figure out what works and what doesn't with an Instant pot. Long story short- if you expect a slow cooker, buy a slow cooker. The Instant Pot &lt;i&gt;will not do the trick&lt;/i&gt;. It won't. That said, I don't hate the thing. It makes the best macaroni and cheese I've ever had the pleasure of enjoying, and it can do meats, soups, even cheesecake really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a number of things that both appliances do really well. For example, pulled meats are really easy with an Instant Pot. Nothing sticks to the bottom, and if you leave a roast in there for a little over an hour it comes out in pieces, ready to be pulled. Just season it, add some water, and hit 'go'. This is really the secret superpower of a crock-pot, however. Do the same thing with a crock-pot, and after about 14 hours or so, you have the same result but with more even flavor. It's not a big difference, but there's a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I've said it before, it's even in the title. An Instant Pot isn't a crock-pot. Don't buy an Instant Pot thinking you can just do away with the old crock-pot when it gets old. They serve different purposes, even if the Instant Pot tries to ape the crock-pot, it really does &lt;i&gt;just that&lt;/i&gt;, it apes it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this mean I think you shouldn't buy an Instant Pot? Honestly, no. I love the thing, and it really does making traditionally long cook time meals quick and easy. It does a lot of things really really well. It's just not a slow cooker. It really, really isn't.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Food"></category><category term="instantpot"></category><category term="food"></category><category term="crockpot"></category><category term="slowcooker"></category><category term="pressurecooker"></category></entry><entry><title>Food!</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/food.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2019-05-14:/food.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We eat every day. It seems obvious, but really think about that. Eating is part of the human experience. For nearly literally all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I really love to cook. Sometimes there's nothing more satisfying than readying a new chili, making burritos, preparing a good steak …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We eat every day. It seems obvious, but really think about that. Eating is part of the human experience. For nearly literally all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I really love to cook. Sometimes there's nothing more satisfying than readying a new chili, making burritos, preparing a good steak dinner, experimenting with pasta, or even just preparing a unique salad. It's a huge world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;This isn't the most intelligent part of this site.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a cook. I'm not. I'd get all sorts of food in my keyboard, since I'd almost certainly set my workstation up in the kitchen if I ever became a cook. It's just how I work. That doesn't mean I don't love it, and it doesn't mean I'm not going to write about it, but I'd make a really poor professional chef. Algorithm-generated meals don't sound too appealing to me, and it's almost certainly one of the first things I would do to speed up production time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all of this said, don't expect professional level advice or insight, I'm just another guy who eats food every day writing about some notable instances of food that comes out really well, or really poorly. If this has you interested, go ahead and pull up the Food Blog window again, and take a look!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will see you there, my fellow food-eating people!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Food"></category><category term="intro"></category><category term="food"></category></entry></feed>