<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>#!/bin/bash it 'till it works - Games</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/feeds/games.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://cannoncontraption.github.io/</id><updated>2022-11-16T17:03:00-05:00</updated><subtitle>The blog of a Zsh user.</subtitle><entry><title>Game Review: Final Fantasy VIII (Remastered)</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/ffviii.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-16T17:03:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T17:03:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2022-11-16:/ffviii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first RPG I ever played to completion was Persona 5 on the PS3. I bought it for something like $15-$20, and finally played more than the intro because I wanted to play down some of my PS3 backlog. While I'm not reviewing Persona 5 any time soon, that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first RPG I ever played to completion was Persona 5 on the PS3. I bought it for something like $15-$20, and finally played more than the intro because I wanted to play down some of my PS3 backlog. While I'm not reviewing Persona 5 any time soon, that did spark my interest in turn-based games. Before that, I had dismissed them entirely as boring, slow-plodding adventures that could range from massively easy to impossible to even pick up. In that regard, I was right, but having never given the genre a chance, I didn't realize that the in-between could be fun, too. For that matter, even the ridiculously easy ones could be fun if they had a good enough setting and story. So, having beaten Persona 5, then 4 (which I had owned for longer on PlayStation 2), I decided to find another RPG to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I settled on Final Fantasy VIII, mostly because I had heard it had a unique and novel approach to the RPG format, which I wanted to try for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;First Impressions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard about this game first from &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/ThatOneVideoGamer"&gt;The Completionist&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube, it was his &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6ZnHW50ChGc"&gt;400th completed game.&lt;/a&gt; So, I hardly went into this game blind. However, his review didn't really sell me on playing the game, he had pretty mixed opinions about it. He said it was good, worth a play, but that you should draw your own conclusions after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So skipping over the rest of the story of how I got the game (I'm honestly not 100% sure at this point, except that it included the soundtrack), let's talk about the intro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro Scenes, First Few Battles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter which platform you bought this on, you ought to start the game on your biggest TV with your best speakers. If this sounds odd to you, don't worry, it would have sounded odd to me, too, had I not already watched the intro on YouTube first. In spite of the fact that this is &lt;em&gt;very much&lt;/em&gt; a PlayStation 1 game, the presentation actually really shines on the big screen. I would argue this holds true to some degree even with the original release, though bear in mind when I say things like this that I did play the HD remaster version, both on PS4 and on PC. You're in for one of the most epic (if unfocused) intro scenes I've ever seen in a video game. If you think watching an epic sword fight mixed with flashes to fully pre-rendered game moments backed by a dramatic (and surprisingly well-composed) Latin choir piece is going to look right on an undocked Switch, I guess that's your call but I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; would recommend giving this the big-screen treatment. It sets up the tone of the game pretty well, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, we switch to the main character in bed, recovering from the sword fight we just saw. This is another touch I really appreciate, some games split their cutscene characters apart from the in-game characters, leading to a really jarring presentation, this isn't one of those games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After wandering around and talking to some characters, we're off to the fire caverns to capture a guardian force (which they unfortunately abbreviate to GF throughout the game). But wait! We can't go yet, you don't know how to junction your GFs! Tutorial time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I've heard a lot of people online say that they hate this game, that it's too complicated or too hard, and they never got into it. These opening tutorials are why, almost without a doubt. The first one stops you in your tracks and explains GF junctioning all at once, before you've fought a single battle. You'll probably kind of get what a GF is just based on what the tutorial is doing, but it's not super clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Junctioning? That's not a word...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, this is where I shift from writing a review to writing a guide on how to play the game. The in-game tutorials suck so badly that I don't feel like I can leave this alone. I'm going to try to explain the system, then walk through a scenario in-game that I think would help you learn this on your own. Again, these first couple tutorials tell you everything you need to know, but they do it like a traditional college lecture does, and you're not going to remember any of it, just like you probably don't remember most of your college (or high school) lectures. It's not a format that's good &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; to teach someone something in any case, games included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters in FFVIII don't have all that many inherent abilities, stat advantages, or progression on their own. Rather, they equip or "junction" a guardian force. This guardian force acts as two different things. First of all, it's a summon. Summoning a guardian force is (for the majority of the game) the most powerful move you can make, but it comes with a time penalty. I'll get into why that's important when I touch on battle. The second use of a guardian force is to impart abilities to the character, and allow them to use magic. This means that which GF each character has equipped ends up being more important than which character has equipped them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've played the Persona series (at least since Persona 3) this should sound pretty familiar. You can think of each character as having the power of the wild card, and the GFs are sort of like personas. They don't impart elemental strengths, weaknesses, or abilities, however. They instead let you adjust certain stats yourself, and they give you the ability to cast any magic you have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each character can then pick 3 in-battle commands (in addition to attack, which every character always has), in addition to a number of abilities. Early game, you don't have any abilities, so it's just battle commands. The starting commands are Magic, Item, GF, and Draw. You'll note though that I just listed four commands, and you can only use three at a time, so you'll need to pick carefully. I recommend GF, Item, then Draw in that order for early game. You'll see why I didn't include magic soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magic is handled &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; differently in FFVIII than most RPGs, including other Final Fantasy games. Rather than using magic points, the game treats each spell like a collectible item. You can collect up to 100 of a single spell, and every time you cast that spell, you take one from the pile. I like to think of it like collecting cards (though the game has that, too). The most basic way to collect more magic is to draw it from enemies. In battle, you can use the Draw command to take some magic from that enemy. You can then either stock that magic, and put it in your own pile, or you can cast it on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where things get somewhat more interesting, and where the junction system becomes really deep. If the GF you have equipped has the ability to junction to a certain stat, you can tie the amount, power, and type of one of your stacks of magic to that stat. For example, if the GF has the ability HP-J, you can junction some magic to your HP stat, raising your HP based on the amount, power, and type of the magic you junction to it. For instance, if I have 25 fires, and I junction that to HP, the max HP of my character will go up. From that point until I have a full pile of fire, if I draw another fire, my character's max HP will rise. Fire isn't healing magic. This means that it's not very closely associated with health. If I were to junction cure instead, each cure spell I have stocked will count for an even greater rise in max HP. Same thing works in reverse for strength (which they abbreviate as 'ST').&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the game, you can also junction an element to your attack. This means if you attack an enemy weak to fire with fire junctioned to your EL-ATK stat, you'll do more damage. If they're strong to fire, you'll do less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summoning a GF&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FFVIII uses Square's somewhat famous "Active Time Battle" system. It's turn based, kind of, but the turns aren't in some set order. Instead, you perform an action as one character, then that character has to recharge for a moment before you can command them again. If you change their speed stat, this changes how quickly they recharge and lets you perform actions as them in battle more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that if you summon a GF, it requires a little time to work. This is why that's important. Whichever character is summoning the GF essentially gets "replaced" by them for a short period, then the GF performs a very powerful magic spell (depending on which one) once enough time has passed. While this is happening, your character's HP gets replaced by the GF's HP. This is nice if you know you're about to get KO'ed but don't have enough health to stop it, since the GF can take the hit (and potentially the fall) for your character. This can stop you from getting a game over, but it means you can't summon that GF until you revive them. It can also be a curse, however, since if you're trying to use their abilities to deal a lot of damage, they could fall mid way through that charge period, meaning you wasted a turn and won't get to summon that GF again until you revive it. You can't revive a GF in battle, so this keeps it from being a silver bullet to never get a game over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Recommended Early-Game Playbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you get to the point where the game starts the GF junctioning tutorial, try your best to follow along. It really does explain everything you need to know, even if it's not doing it in the best way possible. Once it's done, junction each of the two GFs you have to each of the two characters in your party. Which one goes where isn't super important, though they do have varying "compatibility" with each character, which determines how fast that character can summon them. The best combination for compatibility is probably Quezacotl to Squall and Shiva to Quistis, though it's still not a major difference. Then, when asked to pick skills, pick GF, ITem, then Draw in that order. If you would rather pick magic instead of item, that's fine, but don't pick both. Also, remember that using magic has some drawbacks, especially early game when you don't have much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you're junctioned and ready to go, leave the Garden and you'll find yourself on the world map. I don't recommend that you go straight for the fire caverns, however. I would instead recommend that you walk around the opening area and fight a few monsters. Draw some magic from them, and maybe every 2-3 battles or so walk into one of the forests and battle those monsters. If you see a T-Rexaur, escape using R2+L2. Hold them down until your characters run away. Otherwise, all of the monsters in this area should be reasonably easy to defeat. Some of the monsters in the forest have cure, draw as much of this as you can, and then draw-cast it to your characters to keep their health up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between each battle, I would encourage you to jump into the pause menu (triangle on PlayStation, Y on XBOX, I don't know what it is with a keyboard), then select "Junction", pick each character, then select "Auto" and pick one of the options. The game will automatically adjust your character's junctions based on what you pick. If you pick Atk, it optimizes for strength. If you pick Def, it optimizes for HP, etc. You can try the Junction -&amp;gt; Magic option to junction manually, but I would actually recommend you lean on the "Auto" function as much as possible then tweak its recommendations as you see fit from there, rather than trying to manually junction everything yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep doing this until it feels straightforward. It shouldn't take too long, but you'll know what you're doing for much of the game once you're used to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also should know that player level doesn't matter very much, the enemies scale with your level, more or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First Impressions?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to play the opening scenes 4-5 times to figure this out. While I'm glad I did, I'm not sure why I did. The opening cutscene is beautiful, both in sound and visuals, but the actual opening gameplay is an info dump and you're expected to remember all of it. The opening as a whole is therefore kind of mixed, in my opinion. Great atmosphere and character introduction, but horrible tutorials for a completely new gameplay system that's never been used before or since, to my knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, right from the outset you can tell why this game is special. The characters are well developed, and the gameplay is very nearly completely unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Gameplay&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've talked a lot about the gameplay mechanically, but I haven't really put that many opinions in that section. In my opinion, this is the most fun an RPG can get. It's thoughtful, well-balanced (if a little on the easy side), incredibly deep, and almost as easy to mess up as to get right. It encourages a play style that's very counter to most RPGs, where instead of dispatching as many enemies as possible, you're instead trying to squeeze them for all the magic they're worth only to turn around and turn them into playing cards (I'll let you find out how on your own). It's engaging, very tactical, and rewards experimentation even in the tensest moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I can sum up my feelings about the gameplay by talking about how many times I've played the game. I've only finished it once, but I started probably 6-7 saves on PlayStation 4, got about half-way through the game in two of those only to decide I wanted to try the early game again, then got almost to the final area. I then wanted to play the game while on vacation, so I bought it on Steam, played through the first few areas, found out some new stuff about how the SeeD exam works at the beginning, then started a new save file, was underwhelmed by the effects, and played that save to the end anyhow. I enjoyed the moment to moment gameplay enough that this wasn't frustrating, it wasn't boring, and every time I started a new save the characters played completely different. Again, rough beginnings, those first few saves on PlayStation were really just me messing around with the mechanics and re-watching the tutorials to see what I missed, but by the time I got past that, I couldn't put the game down. I played other stuff in the mean time, but every time I switched, I switched back. I'll probably do another playthrough of this game sometime in the near future, which is &lt;em&gt;rare&lt;/em&gt; for someone like me. I'm not a completionist, and I have a backlog of games to play on almost every platform I own. I like experiencing different things when I play a game, not usually exploring it to death to find the last bits of things to do. This might just be an exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout each playthrough, I never ended up playing much Triple Triad, the game's in-game card game. Other than using the cards for other purposes, I never once felt compelled to figure it out and get good at it. I hear that it's become very popular in later games, though, so bear in mind there's this potentially awesome mini-game that you can just play at any time throughout the game that I'm not even going to explain here. There's a lot of gameplay in here for a 4-disc PlayStation game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Story&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit of an odd one. Some people think the story falls apart half-way through, but I don't agree at all. Similar to how the gameplay is unconventional, so is the story. Rather than follow one thread from beginning to end, it wanders a little bit. You're introduced to the world and characters, and then you follow them on their first mission and stick with them as they live. The story doesn't tie up every thread, but it comes very close to exploring every path the characters walk down. It's kind of like reading a really long book with a lot of subplots, you see how the characters behave in all sorts of scenarios, but it has to end at some point, so once the central conflict putting the world in turmoil is solved, the game ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, the story is more concerned with developing the characters than it is with actually telling just one story. I kind of love this, personally, because it ends up enhancing the main story by giving context to each character's perspective on it, but it isn't maybe for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, Squall himself, as our main character, comes across as just mean and unreasonable until about disc 3. The game doesn't tell you that he's 17, and it doesn't tell you why he acts the way he does until the later part of mid way through the game. If you can stick with it, however, he benefits the most from character development, and grows into his role among the cast better than anyone else. I would encourage you not to put the game down because of his behavior early on, there is reason for it and he does wind up redeeming himself by the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would be firmly in favor of a sequel. There's enough left unsaid by the end of the game, in spite of such a well realized world, that I think there's room for more than one spin-off exploring one or more threads, or just straight up sequels. One of the nations in the game world virtually declares war on everyone else, so what happens next? Another nation ends up with a quasi-supernatural destruction machine right next to a major city, not even for the first time. What do they do with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And most importantly, can we see more Laguna? If you know, you know, but Laguna is just amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Graphics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the game is made up of static backgrounds with 3D characters on top. Rather than make symbolic characters from simple polygons like FFVII does, each character is as close as the artists could get to their pre-rendered selves, which means that (in spite of the low-res low-poly world) they all feel consistent. The remaster skews the character models a little bit, they're not exactly faithful to the originals, but had I not said that you'd be totally forgiven for never noticing. This is probably the prettiest PlayStation game I've ever played, remastered or otherwise. I have seen gameplay of the original online, the original graphics are just as good at conveying the game, if not better, so really I have no complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sound Design, Music&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds in the game aren't handled with a ton of care, but honestly that's not such a bad thing. The game is an RPG, so most of the sounds you'll hear are in battle. When you're not in battle, there aren't a ton of things that make sounds, but none of them seem out of place. It's no Halo or anything, but the sound design is competent and isn't distracting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music, on the other hand, is probably the single best PlayStation music I've ever heard. Almost every instrument choice complements the hardware perfectly, and some of the tracks in game sound like CD audio, even though they're constructed in-engine to save RAM. Some of the tracks are CD audio, however, like the opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know Nobuo Uematsu's work elsewhere, you probably have a good idea what to expect. The man is an expert composer, and FFVIII is probably the largest recipient of his best work, only rivaled by FFX, in my opinion. The music nails the atmosphere of the game, and ranges from dramatic, to intense, to serene perfectly. I'm not 100% sure, but I remember finding the soundtrack online was one of the drivers of my decision to ultimately pick up the game. There are a few sequences that get repetitive, but especially for a PlayStation 1 game, this is the bar to reach. The only other soundtrack that I've heard on the platform that comes close is Metal Gear Solid, and even then I would count FFVIII as the superior of the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my favorite turn-based RPG. It's an excellent game, that takes perfect advantage of the hardware it was released on to tell a compelling story with excellently written characters, scored with a unique soundtrack. Did I mention the gameplay is really easy to get lost in? However, it's held back by a few things. Most notably, it doesn't do a very good job of introducing much of anything. What it does explain isn't explained fully, and even then is explained lecture style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Final Fantasy VIII isn't probably for everyone. If you don't have the patience to sit down and figure out its systems, it'll feel tedious. If you don't like turn based RPGs, you might actually still like this one, but I wouldn't bet my life on it. The story introduces more threads than it ties up, and while this works great for developing its characters, it doesn't answer every question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would still consider this a must-try game, however. It runs on absolutely everything, partly because of its age, so if it sounds at all like you would have the patience to try something like this, I strongly encourage you to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="review"></category><category term="game"></category><category term="rpg"></category><category term="remaster"></category></entry><entry><title>The XBOX One</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/xboxonereview.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-09T23:58:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-09T23:58:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2022-11-09:/xboxonereview.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a gently-used XBOX One X from a guy on EBay about a month or two before the Series X launched. This sounds like a really strange time to buy one, they had been recently discontinued, it was clear there was a new generation approaching, I already had a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a gently-used XBOX One X from a guy on EBay about a month or two before the Series X launched. This sounds like a really strange time to buy one, they had been recently discontinued, it was clear there was a new generation approaching, I already had a &lt;a href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/ps4review.html"&gt;PlayStation 4&lt;/a&gt; that I liked a lot, so why did I buy it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Podcast&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a while, I was doing a podcast with a couple of friends called &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCohobbdyZVtRv6PW_BvbRcg"&gt;Idle Circuits&lt;/a&gt;. It was a lot of fun, and I'd love to start it up again, but at the time I had some guilt on my mind. In a couple of our first episodes, I talked pretty harshly about the XBOX family as a whole, but especially the XBONE. I could not understand why anyone would want to buy one, it didn't seem like a very good console at all. The exclusives were fairly thin, the console itself was sleek, but they never decided on one UI to stick to, so it's entirely possible that if you bought an XBONE on launch, you would have to relearn the entire interface if you stuck it in a closet for too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I felt guilty. I had never owned an XBOX up to that point, so I really was taking shots at something I knew nothing about. So, when it showed up on Ebay for $320 in box, I decided it was time to try it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Regrets?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope. Not on either front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don't get the appeal of the XBOX One, or for that matter the Series (S or X). Neither feels like a finished platform to me, mostly because of an unfocused, sloppy UI paired with less compelling exclusives than the PlayStation, an inferior controller, etc. However, I don't regret buying it, if only because I have a PS4 Slim, which isn't nearly as powerful. I do appreciate the ergonomics of the controllers, too, even if I think they're a hilariously dated design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's take it apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;System UI&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a word, the XBOX One feels &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;. It takes an eternity to do just about anything with this interface. If you need a comparison, I can usually start watching a movie on my PlayStation in about half the time (or less) that it takes me to start watching on XBOX. It's not just animation speed, the console takes its sweet time loading everything. The One X is slower than the PS4 slim, let that sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home Screen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn't have a unified design language like the PS4. It's close, but it's harder to describe quickly. The system has pages that you can flip up and down between, each page corresponds to a different category. The main category shows recent apps, a permanent shortcut to the "all apps" screen, and a permanent shortcut to the store. It has some advertisements along the bottom, which I think is a butt move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paging down (which can be done quickly with the triggers) shows different pages, with varying uses. This can be a category of games (what I use it for), a socials page for a particular game, or Microsoft recommendations. It's sort of akin to Android's home screen widgets, they can really serve any purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;All Apps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems really start once you hit "all apps". Here we get a classic "Modern" UI experience. The sidebar includes a number of categories you can page to, like apps, games, "manage", storage, etc. However, at the bottom there's a pie chart and some other (identically formatted) text that &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; actually selectable. You can try, but it won't do anything. If this were anything else, I would expect that to be its own menu page, containing the storage settings, or maybe a more advanced view of something, but it's just a display at the bottom of a menu, hanging out there for no reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That aside, it's functional. The "all apps" screen includes one feature the PlayStation 4 sorely needs, a "check for updates" button that scans everything on the system for updates. The PlayStation requires that you select every game and manually check for updates if you care that everything is up to date. This is admittedly minor, since on the PlayStation downloads are fast, but it would still be nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Settings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to settings, there's one major good thing, and a few bad things. I'm going to talk about the bad things first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two categories that both seem synonymous with each other. One is the "General" section, the other is the "Preferences" section. This seems minor, but neither one describes the contents. The General section includes a mishmash of power saving settings, display and TV settings, accessibility settings, and so on. Preferences, on the other hand, is an overflow section for seldom-used settings, as far as I can see. There's nothing that holds either of these sections together as a defined "category", they're just things that either wouldn't fit elsewhere, or things that Microsoft seems to think belong in the default area. You could easily rename "General" to "Quick Access" and "Preferences" to "Misc" and it would actually mean more than it does now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, there's a section called "System", that does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; include power settings (those are in "General"), but &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; include access controls. The first place I would think to look for access controls is in the "Account" tab, since it has to do with accounts, but not including the power settings in System is just maddening. I vividly remember spending more time than I'd care to admit searching for where the standby setting was, only to realize that it was in General the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the biggest "good thing" about the settings screen is that it even &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; categories. This is a complaint that I see leveled at the PlayStation (and rightfully so) because finding a specific setting that you want is time consuming. It's not really hard, but it takes a fair amount of seeking through long menus to find what you want, and even if the XBOX settings menu isn't very &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt; organized, at the very least it's well &lt;em&gt;paginated&lt;/em&gt;, making it pretty fast to find what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Controllers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I touched on this already, but in my honest opinion the XBOX controller design is just not very good. That's not to say that it's explicitly bad, but it's certainly not the type of quality that you would want out of a current generation system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly, this just boils down to the feature set. The controller itself is fine, but it's lacking in some key areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motion controls?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big no. The XBOX is home to a lot of shooters, and these benefit the most from motion controls, specifically for aiming. If you're not sure what this feels like, there are plenty of videos online talking about it, I would highly recommend the YouTube channel &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/Nerrel"&gt;Nerrel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Battery?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, each XBOX controller ships with a set of Duracells. I don't have anything specific against Duracell, but they're still disposable batteries. It's easy to dismiss this as the cost of better battery life or a good way to save on e-waste since the whole controller isn't junk if its battery wears out, it still encourages you to put regular disposable batteries in the controller. Regardless of what you could do with such a device, most people will take this route over buying rechargeable batteries. In spite of the fact that a single disposable battery isn't much harm to the environment on its own, more than a few quickly becomes significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Repairability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XBOX controllers are difficult to take apart, requiring at minimum the use of a plastic pry tool for each grip of the controller. These hang on tightly, too, which is a good thing from a build quality standpoint, but an annoyance at best when trying to take it apart. This means that entry isn't straightforward, and this alone will stop many people from repairing their own controllers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more damning, however, is their use of security torx screws. Many people don't have security torx, even if they have regular torx. While the drivers aren't specific to the controller and can be had from a garden variety hardware store, they're still a specialized piece of equipment that most people don't have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, once you've gotten inside the controller, they're reasonably easy to take apart and put back together, and the pieces aren't tiny and fragile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impulse Triggers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a neat idea, and I would be very surprised if it wasn't at least partly the inspiration for Sony's later adaptive triggers. Essentially, there's an extra rumble motor in each trigger, providing extra feedback in some games. This works well, where they use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also neat is how the triggers sense a pull. Rather than potentiometers, like in the XBOX 360, the triggers use Hall effect sensors, measuring the distance of a magnet to a sensor inside the controller. This is a very low-wear solution, and it's quite accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less neat is how the impulse triggers are damped against the casing. Rather than cover the surface that the triggers land on when pressed and released, Microsoft opted to use small strips of foam with adhesive tape on the back to stop the triggers from rattling. This works, but it will eventually peel back, exposing the sticky surface of the tape and causing the triggers to stick. Usually they stick in the resting "up" position, but I've had at least one stick in the down position, which killed my race in Forza the first time it happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Own Bias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also need to slot in here that my experience with the XBOX controller hasn't been top-notch. I ordered a pair of them on a Black Friday sale on Microsoft's own website, and only ever received one of the two controllers I ordered. Microsoft support was straight up unhelpful, and I have never received the other controller, nor have I seen a refund. This is not &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; Microsoft's fault, right after I placed the order I heard news about FedEx drivers taking off with game hardware, and this was shipped by FedEx, but nonetheless, I had a tamper-evident box that was wrapped in packing tape and beaten up, no packing slip &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;, no second controller, and no help from Microsoft. I also had no choice in shipping carrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse, that one controller I got is the very same one that first had a sticky trigger. I had been using it for less than a year when it happened, and shortly after it developed stick drift on the left stick as well. I have since repaired the trigger with some craft foam and some epoxy (works great, by the way, someday I may post about that) but I have not fixed the stick drift issue yet. I do want to point out in fairness that these Alps thumbsticks are a problem that is &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; from exclusive to the XBOX controller, the DualShock 4 uses the exact same internals, but this is the only controller I've had it happen to so far. Both problems were well within the first year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermarket Options&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The silver lining here is that there are actually good aftermarket controllers that (almost) reach feature parity. I've found that the PowerA Wired controllers have actually really good thumbsticks, that's usually the part that aftermarket controllers mess up, and they're very inexpensive. If another one of my controllers starts experiencing issues, I will buy another one of these aftermarket pads over the official ones at this point, the only feature they lose is the impulse triggers, and they include a couple of things the first-party ones don't have, like programmable grip buttons. This is the first time I've found a third-party cheap controller that is any good at all, so I feel compelled to mention it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the positive side of the otherwise hilariously dated controller design; it's easier to copy. Motion sensors are a lot harder to get right, as are pressure-sensitive buttons, but something this basic is almost screaming to be cloned, and fortunately there's at least one of these good clones by now. For that matter, the wire is a good thing, too, if for no other reason than you don't have to deal with batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One negative to the PowerA specifically, however, is that the headphone jack is kind of noisy. The noise floor on the first-party controllers is much better. Between this, the wire, and the impulse triggers, make your own decision about which to buy, but the aftermarket is definitely the path I would choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Disc Games&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you stick a disc into a PlayStation, up to at least the PS4, the console reads the disc, maybe installs something, then lets you launch into the game. This does vary from game to game, but most games let you launch in within a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the XBOX One (and by extension probably also the Series X), the console has to first copy the &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; game from the disc to the console. It runs at (by my rough estimate) around 200-300 Mbps or so, so if you have a fast internet connection, you may end up loading into a game faster if you bought it digitally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, my internet connection was 25 Mbps, far below 200, so the disc made sense still. However, games on XBOX seem to like downloading patches the size of the game even more than PlayStation games do. This leaves you with a giant window of time where you're waiting for the game to copy off of the disc, and also to download all of the required updates. It can take a very long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;XBOX Live&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's no PlayStation Network. They do allow free games to be played without a subscription fee, but changing your "Gamer tag"* costs $10. Yuck. Otherwise, I don't have anything notable to say about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Game Pass&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I categorize this as a part of XBOX Live. Strictly speaking, it's not, but it &lt;em&gt;behaves&lt;/em&gt; sort of like a natural extension to a Live subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I can't really talk about the XBOX without bringing up Game Pass. Originally, there was no reason to buy XBOX over PlayStation for anybody, in my opinion. However, if you play a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of multi platform games and you end up spending a lot of money on them, Game Pass makes sense. It lets you play games without buying them, and honestly the experience is pretty good. It's basically the long-coveted "Netflix of Games" that everybody thinks we all need. Even Sony now has something quite similar to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the rub, though. If you don't play a lot of games, or more specifically you don't already play a lot of games on XBOX, this won't make any sense to you. You'll be paying a monthly subscription fee for something that you would honestly not be spending that much money on anyhow, and to top it all off you can get a very similar service now on PlayStation, with their much richer games library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For someone like me, I play a lot of one game for a while, regardless of age, and I buy my games when they're cheap. I don't have a $20 limit on game purchases, but I buy so few of them now because I tend to take my time taking them apart that I end up with a better value for dollar than I would from Game Pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make your own calculation on the value of this, before you decide to jump in. If you do, it's basically just an alternate way to pay for games, just like before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful, though, they do tend to remove games from Game Pass from time to time, so if you start using it regularly you should watch Microsoft's news on the service, lest you find the game you're half-way through suddenly isn't yours to play anymore. Overall, this is the real reason why I don't subscribe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, honestly, everything I've taken issue with is something that you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; put up with. I wouldn't call you crazy for it. The console plays games very well, and there are a lot of (especially multi-platform) games that are well worth your time on the console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it's just not really a standout option over the PlayStation. The experience is notably inferior, and it's lacking some important focus and featureset that the PlayStation has had covered for years by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you already bought one, great, you really shouldn't have any regrets, so long as you don't desperately want to play one of Sony's games. However, if you're looking to buy one, I can really only recommend it if you play a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of games. The less featureful controller, combined with the smaller audience means that you're unlikely to find the absolute best version of a game on XBOX over PlayStation, unless the developer is invested in the platform or owned by Microsoft, but that's not to say that it does its job badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy it if you have one, but temper your expectations if you don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* Cringe name, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit 2022-11-10: Added the "good" part of the settings panel, game pass section, extended the conclusion to match. I also added more information about the controller, including my own bias and the section about PowerA (whom I have no business relationship with, to be perfectly clear)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="XBOX"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="games"></category><category term="consoles"></category></entry><entry><title>Console Review: the PlayStation 4</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/ps4review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-08T23:59:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T23:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2022-08-08:/ps4review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a used Playstation 4 Slim in late 2017 from GameStop with a PSVR. I've been using it fairly regularly ever since. Now that we're a few years into the lifetime of the PS5 and I've had some time to put off buying one, I thought it would be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a used Playstation 4 Slim in late 2017 from GameStop with a PSVR. I've been using it fairly regularly ever since. Now that we're a few years into the lifetime of the PS5 and I've had some time to put off buying one, I thought it would be the perfect time to start reviewing the PS4 and its contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Hardware&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PS4 is powered internally by an AMD Radeon GPU based on an early version of their GCN architecture. GCN was able to hang onto life even in the desktop space from 2012 or 2013 all the way up until 2019 without really falling too far behind in the product categories it competed in, so this component is pretty strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the PS4 is also powered by an 8-core version of the AMD Jaguar mobile CPU. So, the PS4 has 8 "cores" of computing power at its disposal, all within a strict power budget. In reality, that's 4 cores with 8 integer units between them, like most of AMD's CPUs of the time. This is weak, and I'll touch on where this becomes a problem later, but this is just some foreshadowing. It sucks. It works, but it sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system comes equipped with 2 front-facing USB ports (yuck), and physical power and eject buttons. It has the usual set of ports on the back for a cheap modern console, power, 8P8C Ethernet, HDMI, and a mystery "AUX" port used by the camera and basically nothing else. It has a Blu-Ray drive above the power and eject buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a design aesthetic perspective, the system is solidly serviceable. It's an unassuming black slanted package, which I hear is designed to help hide the cables when it's lying flat. There's a slice in the middle, through which all of the system's airflow happens. The USB ports and the majority of the I/O are in this slice, and the power/eject buttons are on the top face of the bottom slanted segment. Again, it's serviceable. Nobody is going to look at your home theater cabinet and point to it as particularly ugly, or beautiful. It does come in different colors, if you want to get fancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Controllers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a few words, these are best in class. They've got the broadest range of features out of all of the controllers of the time, featuring traditional rumble (no gimmicks), analog triggers and joysticks, a trackpad, gyro and accelerometer sensors for motion, a light bar for tracking by the camera (VR, AR applications). The usual Sony face buttons are present, along with a traditional D-Pad. There's also a "Share" button for the social side of the console. The controller is charged via micro-USB (hate it or love it, it's what was available at the time, C did not exist yet), and it has an accessory port and a headset jack on the bottom between the thumbsticks. It uses a rechargeable internal LiPo battery. To service the controller, you need to remove a total of 4 screws on the outside, and a few more inside. On the whole, there are no nasty hidden snaps (that I remember, open with care since I haven't done this in a while on a fresh controller or just ask someone else).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a bone to pick with people who say the DualShock has 4 buttons rather than a D-Pad. This is false. Sony made the design decision of molding the case in front of the D-Pad, but I encourage you to take it apart if you don't believe me. It's got the same center post as any other controller, and the actual pad itself is indeed one piece. You can't push left and right at the same time unless you broke your controller. Actually, this plastic molding decision has one huge benefit- it's really easy to determine where the middle of the D-Pad is by just feel. There's no guesswork about where center is since the molding on the case is a set line that your finger will always feel. In addition, since it's a cross shape, you can often times even tell where your finger has drifted to if it has drifted. The Steam controller and Xbox One controllers both fail in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a variety of reasons, the DualShock 4 is probably still the best controller you can buy for PC use, too. It has a standard set of functions with no extra bits nobody supports, and Steam Input lets you map the gyro sensors to aiming, so that you can properly play Halo with a controller. It uses Bluetooth to connect to the PlayStation, and supports traditional pairing by holding the Share button while you power the controller on. The light bar will flash in a unique way when you've got it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of you think the PS4 controller's thumbsticks are a little stiff, and honestly I can't deny that they're not perfect in that regard. However, the thumbsticks are internally virtually identical to the Xbox controller's. This means you can buy a set of replacement thumbcaps for the Xbox One or Xbox Series controllers and simply install them. This will give you exactly the same thumbstick weighting as the Xbox controller. If you want to go extra fancy, you can even install the thumbsticks from the Elite controller, giving you swappable magnetic caps. At that point, the only difference with the thumbsticks is the position of the left stick. I've been able to adapt to each style since the first time I tried without issue, but I hear some people have problems with this, so make your own decisions. If you don't own an Xbox, I would recommend getting used to this style, myself. If your thumb starts slipping off the left stick during an intense action sequence, if you have my size hands you can reach across with your right thumb and hold the stick while you re-position your left thumb. This is much harder with inverted sticks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ergonomically, the controller is serviceable. It's not offensive or impressive, but it works and I don't have any major complaints. It's not particularly heavy and the triggers don't require much force to actuate when Steam is set to hair trigger, making it a great choice for FPS games and motion aim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Software&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where the PS4 really starts to stand out. Sony's logic with the interface is generally really consistent, just like it was with the PS3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Main Menu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The home screen is sorted into 3-4 rows of icons. At the top are system-level settings. These are above where your cursor sits by default when you start the console, and include system settings, account settings, trophies, and chat functions among other things. The second row is a list of the most recently installed/played games, sorted by how recently the game has been launched/installed, and included in this list are any folders. If you play a game in a folder, the whole folder is promoted to the top of the list rather than pulling the game out of it. Folders work much like the recent line, but they have a fixed order. They remember which item in the folder was last used, so it's always available. Going into the third row (fourth if in a folder) is details about the game. Somewhat annoyingly, you need to be online for this to work, but it includes links from the developers of the game, streams, trophies, and fun facts about who else in your PSN friends list is playing the game and what trophies they got. That's about all there is to the logic of the home screen, but there are occasions where you can press "options" to bring up a context menu. This works like right click on a PC, so it's also pretty easy to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just typed a lot about that menu. What I want you to come away with though is that that's a pretty complete operating manual for the system menu. There's very few exceptions to that general structure, and finding things is usually very quick and easy. About the only thing worth mentioning is that they call "Eject" "Remove Disk" in the system menu, so if you see it, that's just Eject not a 'delete everything' button. This represents a trend towards over-simplifying everything to avoid confusion, which usually makes things more confusing. You could probably guess I'm against this trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sony's library with the PS4 is world-class. They have among the best console exclusives ever launched, such as Ghost of Tsushima, God of War (PS4), Ratchet and Clank (PS4), Uncharted 4, DriveClub, Horizon Zero Dawn (now on PC, but the port happened around when the PS5 launched), Persona 5 Royal, and many, many more. Those are just what came to mind. Because it's a comparatively powerful system next to its contemporaries, most multi-platform games play their best on PS4 out of all the consoles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Games also don't need to fully install to disk to play. Most of them will launch within a few seconds of putting them in the disk drive. Those of you with Xbox Ones will probably find this very refreshing, the difference is dramatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Web Browser&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful to turn off JavaScript. The browser isn't very well optimized, and JavaScript makes most pages absolutely useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The browser also doesn't support a lot of tabs open at once. You'll need to be careful not to leave anything important open, since if you open too many other things (first of all the performance will suck, but at any rate) the tab may disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This goes for any console, but just avoid the browser. The CPU isn't strong enough to support it properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also note on the topic of CPU that the CPU also limits some games somewhat, so even if a low-end old computer with a similar GPU can run a game, don't expect you'll get exactly the same performance out of the PS4. It may be better if it's optimized for the specific GPU in the PS4, or it may be worse because that CPU is so weak. It's weak enough it was a talking point on launch back in 2013, and almost 10 years later things certainly haven't gotten better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, that was a dry review. I don't have a whole lot more to say about the PS4 without bringing in a lot more about the other three big consoles of the time (Wii U, XB1, Switch), so I'll save that for later. Suffice it to say I'm not sure whether I have more PS4 disks or Steam games right now, and whichever library is larger is larger by a very small amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't have one and you've never owned a PlayStation, buy a PS4 off of someone who just got a PS5. The library is vast and enormously high-quality. The PS4 also sold really, really well for a home console, currently the second-best selling home console. Finding one shouldn't be an issue, as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't mention this before, but the PS4 also does not need to ever go online to function. That makes it in a class of its own in terms of usability into the future, there are no major functions that you lose out on in terms of playing games, either. As far as I remember, even trophies work offline (though don't quote me, they're very careful to prevent people from hacking trophies they haven't earned so the system does require a time sync for that if the clock battery has died). If you put it in the attic for 20 years and it works when you pull it out, all of your downloaded and surviving disc games will continue to work just fine. That's actually the main reason I consider buying disc games, they can survive both the individual console I own and the online services and still retain a copy of the game for me. If that sounds good to you, you'll like the PS4 quite a lot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I give it a 994. You can decide the scale for yourself, since whatever number I give it is meaningless; just make sure it's on the positive end, since I don't have anything major to complain about, just minor nitpicks I'll mention in future posts about the other consoles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="PlayStation"></category><category term="tech"></category><category term="games"></category><category term="ps4"></category></entry><entry><title>Ratchet and Clank (PS2) Review</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/ratchet-and-clank-ps2-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2020-12-28:/ratchet-and-clank-ps2-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;1. Introduction
&lt;a name="1. Introduction"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;The Ratchet and Clank series has
been getting a lot of buzz lately, what with the trailers
for the new PS5 entry, Rift Apart. However, the series got
its start way back in 2002 on the PS2, as Insomniac
Games&amp;rsquo; first entry on the platform. This particular
series …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;1. Introduction
&lt;a name="1. Introduction"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;The Ratchet and Clank series has
been getting a lot of buzz lately, what with the trailers
for the new PS5 entry, Rift Apart. However, the series got
its start way back in 2002 on the PS2, as Insomniac
Games&amp;rsquo; first entry on the platform. This particular
series is, in my opinion, the single best 3D platforming
series ever released, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m
alone in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1.1. Personally
&lt;a name="1.1. Personally"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;I got my start with the series
on the PS3. Ratchet and Clank Future: A Crack in Time was
the second game I ever played on PS3, behind the original
Little Big Planet. Having grown up mostly with the Nintendo
Entertainment System and a relatively weak
&amp;quot;multimedia&amp;quot; PC, the experience was mind-blowing
to me. Watching what was essentially a computer game render
visuals with particle effects everywhere, a 3D world I could
run around in, the massive number of things on screen, it
captivated me. As if the visuals weren&amp;rsquo;t enough, the
sound design and soundtrack in that game are among the best
ever made, certainly up to that point, but even now the
experience still holds up remarkably well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;My first interaction with the
first game, however, was much later on. The first time I
played it was in the Ratchet &amp;amp; Clank Collection, on PS3.
The graphics and sound were of course much more primitive
than the technical showpieces that are the PS3 entries I had
played up to that point, but nevertheless it felt like much
the same game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1.2. Game Basics
&lt;a name="1.2. Game Basics"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Core to the Ratchet and Clank
series is the usual 3D-platforming challenges, a diverse set
of enemies with different attack styles, and an enormous
arsenal of weaponry in various amusing and cartoonish forms.
Interspersed with this are occasional racing or puzzle
sections, that require either quick thinking, mastery of a
DualShock, or careful consideration and planning. Usually
it&amp;rsquo;s a mix of all of this. I believe it&amp;rsquo;s for
reasons of easy adaptability to new concepts and hardware
that Sony chose to make another Ratchet and Clank be one of
the showpieces of PS5 launch marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;The focus of Ratchet and Clank
is combat-readiness first, platforming chops second.
You&amp;rsquo;ll need both to a degree, but there&amp;rsquo;s a lot
more focus on the gun- and wrench-play than on tricky camera
setups and precise jumps. This, in my opinion, makes it a
lot more approachable to modern (2020) audiences than many
of its contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Controls
&lt;a name="2. Controls"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;So yes, as a warning, you should
have an original controller for whatever PlayStation the
Ratchet and Clank you&amp;rsquo;re interested came out on.
Aftermarket controllers work, but they often make the game
much harder to play. In the case of Ratchet and Clank 1,
that would be a DualShock 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;This, in my opinion, is one of
the great strengths of the game. Most of the series,
possibly all of it, shares this in common- while not every
feature of the console the game launched on is used, the
developers aren&amp;rsquo;t afraid to take advantage of
what&amp;rsquo;s unique and special about that system. In the
case of the PS2 that&amp;rsquo;s the controller, as I mentioned.
However, the game does this without feeling like features
got shoehorned in or slapped on for no reason- if a feature
of a controller is used, for example, it&amp;rsquo;s done
because whatever mechanic uses that feature is uniquely
suited to it. Analog buttons, for example, are used in
swimming in the game. Not only do you have the option of
ascending and descending underwater, but you can control
that by changing the pressure of your finger on the X and
square buttons. A similar story is true for jumping, though
arguably this could be done as well to a reasonable degree
with a digital button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Beyond just the featureset of
the controller, the controls in Ratchet and Clank are...
fine. They work, they don&amp;rsquo;t feel super awkward or
silly, but they&amp;rsquo;re certainly among the roughest in the
series. For example, the lack of a strafe function is
annoying, even though there&amp;rsquo;s a button basically free
for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Where the control set really
seems odd is in its choice to duplicate buttons. Both sets
of shoulder buttons generally do the same thing. So, while
in the PS3 Ratchet and Clank games, you can use R1 to fire
your equipped weapon, R1 is crouch in the original, and so
is R2. There are some minor areas where one set has a
different function from the other, but it&amp;rsquo;s rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Graphics
&lt;a name="3. Graphics"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Ratchet and Clank is...
inoffensive in terms of graphics. It probably won&amp;rsquo;t
blow your mind, even as PS2 games go, but it&amp;rsquo;s also
not hideous. It&amp;rsquo;s stylized enough that the world fits
with itself, the graphics don&amp;rsquo;t get in the way of
this. However, it still retains a lot of flat polygonal
objects, and there are some cut corners when it comes to
things like rounded edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;As you would expect, the
particle effects are rough and dated, the character models
aren&amp;rsquo;t super detailed, and there&amp;rsquo;s not very much
in the world that could be used to relate scale to the real
world. It&amp;rsquo;s part of the charm of the game in a way,
but if you&amp;rsquo;re not into that sort of thing I could see
the sort of random scale of some objects being an issue. If
you can play Half-Life without any issue, you&amp;rsquo;ll be
fine here, too. However, when put together, what really are
just technical limitations contribute immensely to the style
of the game, making it feel a little bit more like
you&amp;rsquo;re inside a cartoon. The basic particle effects
are maybe the only thing that breaks this a little bit, but
even then it&amp;rsquo;s nothing to really break the experience
overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not to say I
don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy the graphics in this game. I think
what&amp;rsquo;s especially impressive is that they managed to
get long, detailed, winding stages all to fit into memory on
the PS2 without awkward loading screens in the middle of a
planet or a path. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve landed, you aren&amp;rsquo;t
waiting for anything to load off of disk, which contributes
immensely to the feeling of immersion that the game&amp;rsquo;s
world provides. Given that the game was released two years
in to the lifespan of the PS2 (which itself is notoriously
difficult to develop for) and that this is Insomniac&amp;rsquo;s
first PS2 title, what they pulled off with the hardware is
still impressive, despite its shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Sound
&lt;a name="4. Sound"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4.1. Sound Effects
&lt;a name="4.1. Sound Effects"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;This is one area where the
collection falls flat. If you care a lot about audio in your
PS2 games for some reason, play this on the PS2. The PS3
gets the pitch wrong in a bunch of places, which renders
some features of a couple gadgets useless (most affected
being the metal detector).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Sound on the PS2 is fine for a
PS2 game. It won&amp;rsquo;t win any awards, it&amp;rsquo;s dated at
best and has a few harsh sounds that some people will find
annoying, like a lot of (especially older) games, but
it&amp;rsquo;s no so bad as to ruin the experience. Again, it
fits with the style of the game, and where in history it
belongs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Sound effects are generally
basic. There&amp;rsquo;s quite a lot of pitch shifting involved,
which can sometimes make the different sounds sound
interesting, but usually the developers use this for an
over-exaggerated Doppler effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4.2. Music
&lt;a name="4.2. Music"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;The soundtrack to the original
is very much computer generated. It wears this proudly on
its sleeve, and while it does occasionally try to mimic a
real instrument, it generally doesn&amp;rsquo;t do this in a
totally blatant, tasteless way, and once again the way that
instruments are used contributes somewhat to the aesthetic
of the game. Of course there are ups and downs in this one,
just like any soundtrack, but by the time the game is done
very few of the tracks should have worn out their welcome,
and if one did it won&amp;rsquo;t have probably played for all
that long past that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;However, that&amp;rsquo;s something
I should also put in context. Relative to what most other
soundtracks of the time were like, this one is a great
example of well-composed music matched excellently to each
environment. The music beautifully complements the game
world, both of them feeling dated, but in a pleasant,
nostalgic kind of way for a modern audience, rather than a
tacky, tasteless way. Despite any minor complaints I make
about the soundtrack, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t switch it for
anything, even at its weakest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. Game World
&lt;a name="5. Game World"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5.1. Story
&lt;a name="5.1. Story"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to try my best
not to spoil anything here, but the &amp;quot;Save the solar
system&amp;quot; premise presented within the first 10 minutes
of the game is fairly true to what the game is. It does
require some suspension of disbelief, since the hero of the
story is basically a kid who made a starship using a wiki in
his backyard, not some galactic authority. However,
overlooking this the story is sufficient to keep the game
engaging, and to give some stakes to everything the
character does in that world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;The writing is generally pretty
smart, and while not every joke in the game is going to be
to everyone&amp;rsquo;s taste, the game is overall very
lighthearted, especially considering one of the core tools
the character has is an enormous arsenal of insane weaponry
and various other massive mayhem making mechanisms. In fact,
I would go so far as to say that even given that it was the
original in the series, Ratchet and Clank has some of the
better writing of all of the games in the series. It has its
rough edges, and unfortunately portrays Ratchet as a whiny
teenager, rather than the level-headed awkward fun-guy from
the later games. However, the way this story is told makes
Ratchet and Clank&amp;rsquo;s friendship in the later games make
a lot more sense. In this early game, they start out as
total strangers. Ratchet especially views his relationship
with Clank at first as transactional, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem
to be seeking companionship at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;I want to note briefly here that
in this respect, I think the original game far outpaces the
2016 remake. The new game is good as well, but story-wise
the original introduces the characters and knits them
together in a much more logical way. You know why Ratchet
and Clank stick together, it&amp;rsquo;s not something that just
happens out of nowhere with no explanation or story behind
it other than just pure availability of another character in
the vicinity when robots attack. While we&amp;rsquo;re on the
subject, the tone of the original is, at least in my
opinion, much more suited to the kind of game that any
Ratchet and Clank really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5.2. Environments
&lt;a name="5.2. Environments"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;The different planets the
characters explore, and overall the setting in general is
something that contributes a lot to the game. Starting off
in the middle of nowhere, then proceeding to explore nearly
abandoned spaceships and stations, toxic worlds filled with
poisonous gas, worlds covered in ocean, ice worlds, each
with their own challenges unique to that world adds a great
amount of depth to the game. A lot of the puzzle of the game
is simply figuring out the best way to conquer an
environment. Graphically, most of these areas are fairly
primitive, and some of them feel mechanically similar, but
it almost always feels like there&amp;rsquo;s something unique
about each place. It&amp;rsquo;s also unique to see flying
chainsaws that aren&amp;rsquo;t trying to kill your character,
and find yourself not really questioning it. This may be the
ultimate test of a game world- can you believe it? If not,
do you need to? By the way, I feel I can spoil this much
safely- if you manage to shoot down one of those flying
chainsaws, it gives you a bolt- while not worth much,
it&amp;rsquo;s still kind of fun to see if you can manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5.3. Side Missions
&lt;a name="5.3. Side Missions"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;On the whole, this is a linear
game. Side missions aren&amp;rsquo;t the focus here at all.
However, there are some alternate paths you can take.
Sometimes these are more obvious than others, but the side
areas and the main quest path feel incredibly similar. This
means that it&amp;rsquo;s easy to choose the wrong one in some
cases, and travel down the side path thinking it was the
story path. Unfortunately for those who like a quick, linear
game, the only way to know that all paths are completed is
to travel through the start menu for a minute and find the
missions page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;There generally aren&amp;rsquo;t
side missions per se, as a result. However, there are
gadgets and items that can be collected by visiting side
paths. They usually come with mission items in the missions
screen marked as just &amp;quot;Explore the Destroyed City&amp;quot;
and things along those lines. If there&amp;rsquo;s something
major to explore (as in not a gold bolt, etc.) then there
will be a mission item for it marked in the missions
page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Each of these side paths result
in a reward of some sort, and the vast majority end up being
well worth it. Unlike future games, for example, gold bolts
are not just used for unlocking cosmetics in-game, but are
instead used to buy gold weapons. This becomes incredibly
useful, especially in late game or in new game+ (which is
NOT challenge mode in this entry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Overall, my advice in most
Ratchet and Clank games is to follow all of the side paths
completely. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t want the reward at the
end, one of the common tasks in the game is grinding for
bolts. It&amp;rsquo;s not strictly required, you can get by
without doing it, however there&amp;rsquo;s almost always some
weapon or item that would make the game that much more fun
that requires a great sum of bolts (or later other
currencies) to obtain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Usually, Ratchet and Clank games
have some specific mini-game challenges, and in this game
that&amp;rsquo;s just hoverboard racing. Everything else is
generally just the usual platforming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;5.3.1. Hoverboard Races
&lt;a name="5.3.1. Hoverboard Races"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;Being perfectly honest,
I&amp;rsquo;m a little bit conflicted about these. The races
control like a kart racer just as much as anything.
There&amp;rsquo;s in-air steering, powerups, accelerator pads,
etc. etc. There&amp;rsquo;s no such thing as a twitch reaction
due to the heavy use of slow tank controls, and
there&amp;rsquo;s a heavy penalty for missing an accelerator
pad, or crashing. Given that both of these are easy to do,
the races certainly take some practice and patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;These races usually also have
crates all over the place, which can make for a fun
additional target. Participation in races isn&amp;rsquo;t a
terribly great way to earn bolts, but at least the first few
times through a course there&amp;rsquo;s something to be
collected if you have built up the skill to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;There are two courses in the
game, one in Blackwater City on Rilgar, fairly early in the
game, and a required race on Kalebo later in the game. While
the Blackwater City race is strictly optional, I strongly
suggest everyone play it. Between the two courses, this is
the easier one, and the prize for first place, while not
strictly required, makes the later race MUCH easier.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to understate this- while the prize you get
only matters in races, you&amp;rsquo;ll spend a similar amount
of time racing either way, you&amp;rsquo;ll enjoy it a lot more
if you win the first race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6. Conclusions
&lt;a name="6. Conclusions"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;In conversation I don&amp;rsquo;t
give people number scores for a game, I don&amp;rsquo;t think
that really gives a good impression of a game on its own.
However, I&amp;rsquo;m going to bury one way down at the bottom
here, to sort of give my overall impressions. I give Ratchet
and Clank a 56/64. It was a solid start to an even more
solid game, and despite my nitpicks with it, it&amp;rsquo;s not
a case where having played the later games the original is
no longer playable or enjoyable. The earliest games in the
series hold up almost as well as the later entries, and is
certainly worth playing if you can get your hands on a
copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;7. A Note on the Ratchet and Clank Collection
&lt;a name="7. A Note on the Ratchet and Clank Collection"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;If this is the way you find the
game, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth picking up. However, it runs
only at 720p, not 1080 like you might expect for a simpler
game running on PS3. Also, it does have a few more framerate
dips than the original. That said, the first game is fine
here, at any rate. I would advise getting the PS2 original
for any of the later games, however. At my best guess, the
engine from the first game was ported, and all of the newer
games run on that. This is fine to simply play the games,
but with my experience with the third game, even running on
an HDTV it looks far better on the PS2. There are various
blur and depth of field effects that sell some environments
(like underwater) where in the collection it looks like a
cheap PS2 game. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a case where that should
stop you from trying the game, again, but bear it in mind
when playing through.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="game"></category><category term="review"></category></entry><entry><title>Games!</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/games.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2020-12-18:/games.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;I Play Video Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t really anything
special these days, but I figure that at this point
I&amp;rsquo;ve probably played enough video games to have some
meaningful comments on them from time to time. This section
will be where I talk about games, gaming, what I&amp;rsquo;m …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;I Play Video Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t really anything
special these days, but I figure that at this point
I&amp;rsquo;ve probably played enough video games to have some
meaningful comments on them from time to time. This section
will be where I talk about games, gaming, what I&amp;rsquo;m
playing, the state of the industry, so on and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;While not a terribly unique
position, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing games most of my life,
starting on PC and on the original Nintendo (some of you
probably know it best as the NES). While these days all my
PC gaming is on Linux, I have four of the five Playstations,
an Xbox One X, a Nintendo, a Super Nintendo, and a FireCore
Genesis. This, in my opinion, gives me a wide base of gaming
experience to draw upon. As someone technical, I believe I
also have a basic understanding of how each of these
consoles work, as well as their strengths and
weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-top: 1em"&gt;So if any of this sounds
interesting, please stay tuned! Hopefully this section will
prove entertaining and informative to you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="games"></category><category term="intro"></category></entry></feed>