<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>#!/bin/bash it 'till it works - Misc</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://cannoncontraption.github.io/</id><updated>2023-01-24T23:42:00-05:00</updated><subtitle>The blog of a Zsh user.</subtitle><entry><title>Analog Watch Superiority</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/analogwatch.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-24T23:42:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-24T23:42:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2023-01-24:/analogwatch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I didn't tend to wear a watch, with the exception of Boy Scout camp. I needed to know the time then, and there aren't any wall clocks outside, unfortunately. I would say we should fix that, meaning it in a tongue-in-cheek way, but I know …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I didn't tend to wear a watch, with the exception of Boy Scout camp. I needed to know the time then, and there aren't any wall clocks outside, unfortunately. I would say we should fix that, meaning it in a tongue-in-cheek way, but I know somebody would take it seriously and I do not want that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, I got my Zune HD, that showed the time just fine, then a cell phone. Then came smartwatches, and I started wearing a watch all the time. I was constantly frustrated that all of the smartwatch faces seemed to be analog, seeing limited options for digital. Then I moved back to dumb watches, but this time wearing them everywhere. If you're interested in the full story, check out &lt;a href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/watchjourney.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; that I'm also posting today as a bonus. Digging it up was part of the inspiration for this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was 2019 when I finally decided to start wearing an analog watch on purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;From Hate to Great&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the old days, I always got frustrated when someone asked the time and I couldn't come up with a precise answer quickly. I'd stare at the dial, blankly say "umm..." then spit out a number that was far too accurate and probably should have been generalized a bit. However, I got asked this a lot less once I left college, so it was less of a priority. Also, I finally decided that precision like that wasn't a flex. So, I went from caring that I had digital on my wrist, to not being super concerned one way or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first reason I started to care about wearing analog was style. Digital watches tend to be pretty ugly, and while I won't say that I have the best fashion sense or anything, I appreciated the aesthetics of a physical dial even before I figured out their practical advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when I saw &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NeopkvAP-ag"&gt;this video on Technology Connextras&lt;/a&gt; I virtually stopped wearing my digital watches entirely, until my primary daily wear watch stopped. I'll get into that in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll sum up the video by saying that the hands on the clock act like a pie chart, showing progression through time rather than a numerical representation of progression through time. It's basically one step closer to the actual passage of time than a number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top comment on the video almost does a better job of describing this effect, quoting (supposedly) Douglas Adams writing to his editor in 1992:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"(...) there is something inherently ridiculous about digital watches (...) Digital watches came along at a time that, in other areas, we were trying to find ways of translating purely numeric data into graphic form so that the information leapt easily to the eye. For instance, we noticed that pie charts and bar graphs often told us more about the relationships between things than tables of numbers did. So we worked hard to make our computers capable of translating numbers into graphic displays. At the same time, we each had the world’s most perfect pie chart machines strapped to our wrists, which we could read at a glance, and we suddenly got terribly excited at the idea of translating them back into numeric data, simply because we suddenly had the technology to do it..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't checked this to make sure it's really Adams, but I don't think I have to given how much he tended to write in digital watches while talking about absurd little humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;I don't buy digital watches anymore.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what really prompted the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2019 when I was first buying an analog watch for the purpose of it being an analog watch, I did my usual thing and kept to an extreme budget. I don't like to spend any more than I have to on basically anything, and I want it to last for as long as is humanly possible. If I can make a $1 tool last my lifetime, that's a win in my books. So, naturally, I bought a couple of white-box $10 watches. One of these watches had a larger dial* and was fairly minimal looking, but it was kind of big and the strap was uncomfortable. I decided to reserve this for special occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other watch was something fairly special though, as far as style and form go. It had a smaller dial that fit very nicely on my wrist, with a nylon weave band. Its steel housing developed this wonderful wear pattern over time that made it look like it was designed to look worn, like an old tool. The tarnish around the outside showed fabulously when caught in the right light, but it didn't look out of place either. Furthermore, it disappeared on my wrist, it was insanely comfortable to wear compared to what I was used to up to that point. So, it was my daily driver for a couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I caution you not to buy something like that, though, since at some point in early 2022 it started to get stuck whenever the seconds hand hit the 52 second mark. It wouldn't do this every time, but when it did it would lose track of time. This erratic drifting issue made it a lot less useful. Here's a picture of it, stopped and mostly reassembled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="my current favorite watch" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/analogwatch/rip.jpg" width="50%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people (myself included at the time of purchase) would have just said something like "it's so cheap you could just buy another one!" but there's a few problems with this. Firstly there's waste. I tried to figure out a way to even look at the movement to see what was going wrong, but as far as I can tell it's welded plastic, meaning I'll never get it back together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, part of its charm was the wear it was developing, and I'd have to start that all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as importantly, I'd have to go buy another one. I mentioned this before, but I don't particularly like buying things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll mention for the sake of fairness that the band had started to fall off, and it was after it had fallen earlier in the day that the sticking issues started to show up. I wound up missing my train over that, which fortunately wasn't a huge deal since it was the end of the day, not the beginning. However, I should have at least tried replacing the pins that hold the band in place first, and I didn't. That said, it's also possible that the lugs had started to become worn, in which case the pins wouldn't have helped anyhow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, though, I've missed my old analog watch, so I did two things. Firstly, I bought some smaller Casio analogs online. I've had &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt; luck with their digital watches so far, and I've heard rave reviews about their analog ones as well. As a bonus, they're also cheap! You can get a Casio analog for about the same price as a Casio digital, they start around $13-$15 at the time of writing. Again, I bought two of them, something minimal, and something rugged. Their model numbers are &lt;em&gt;insane&lt;/em&gt; so I won't list them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing that I did was try to swap the watch bands on my cheap watches, to see what effect that would have. I never checked until now, but it turns out that one of them uses an 18mm band, and the other a 20mm band, so that was out. However, it occurred to me that my old Asus Zenwatch used a 20mm band, as did my Pebble. The stock band on the Zenwatch broke about a year after I bought it, and I replaced it with a canvas band I found online for $20. I overpaid for it, but it's wonderfully constructed and very comfortable. Lo and behold, I've been wearing the watch for a couple of days now, and it's pretty comfortable. The band even matches, more or less:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="big cheap watch, new band" src="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/images/analogwatch/newband.jpg" width="50%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, it's a lot closer to a match in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Lessons Learned with Cheap Analogs&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would still recommend a very cheap digital watch. Not much can fail on those, since they're solid-state. However, with an analog watch, buy a name brand. I'll probably get destructive on my old watch out of curiosity, but I have a sinking feeling there's going to be a broken part in there. Don't miss your train over that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all watches, if you don't like the comfort of the watch, swap the band out for one that's a bit more flexible, there's a good chance it'll feel a lot better after that. I wound up avoiding the larger watch because the two-piece band it came with was stiff as a wet piece of plywood, and while my tastes have moved on aesthetically since when I bought it, I appreciate having it around all the same at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good argument for name brands can be seen in the second photo. You'll notice what looks like some dirt on the lower half of the dial. That wasn't there when I bought the watch, and it's under the crystal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people will also tell you that acrylic crystals are less durable than mineral or sapphire crystals, but honestly none of my watches have gotten notably scratched at all, so bear in mind your wear level on things before making that a sticking point when buying a new watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, wear an analog watch if you can. I would encourage you to try it just to see if it makes the difference to you that it does for me, but I honestly tell time better with one. I'm late for things less often, and I misjudge how long it will take me to do things and how long I have less often. Just skip the $10 white box ones, lest you find you like it only to have it die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* You'll want to look up watch terminology if you're already lost. I learned it as a kid from a build-it-yourself watch kit that broke within a week, but if you weren't lucky enough to have one of those, no matter how long it ultimately lasted, knowing the terms will help you should you decide to comparison shop. It will also help you read this article.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="electronics"></category><category term="style"></category><category term="theory"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>My Journey in Watches</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/watchjourney.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-24T23:41:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-24T23:41:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2023-01-24:/watchjourney.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this initially as some placeholder text for a blog theme I was creating at the time, but since it's relevant to the article I'm actually writing today, I figured I'd post it as a bonus for anyone who's crazy enough to be interested. I wrote it back in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this initially as some placeholder text for a blog theme I was creating at the time, but since it's relevant to the article I'm actually writing today, I figured I'd post it as a bonus for anyone who's crazy enough to be interested. I wrote it back in September, but even by then some of the text was outdated, and you'll see why in &lt;a href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/analogwatch.html"&gt;the other article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Dumb Watches&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I had an $11 Wal-Mart watch that I was quite fond of. It really was nothing special, but I had tried to replace it many times over the course of many years, and every replacement ended up wearing out or getting lost, but this one stuck around. Part of that was that I could never get myself to wear a watch regularly. It always seemed like a good idea, but a good idea isn't very useful if you don't act on it. So, it sat in random places for years, not really gathering dust at all because I would move it out of the way of other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Enter the Smartwatch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a big believer in smartwatches by the time 2014 rolled around. When I first heard about the Pebble, I thought about all of the things I could use it for, and I had no shortage. I had some classmates who would badger me with questions and "hey u there?" over and over again, so I felt it would be nice to see their texts on screen. I also listened to music a lot, and having a pause button on my wrist would be nice. I also liked the idea of changeable watch faces, something that we don't really have anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I took the plunge. I bought a first generation Pebble, and I loved it. Up until 2016, anyhow, when the screen delaminated and I could no longer use it. However, I got so much use out of it. When I was driving with my phone plugged into my car's AUX jack, I could safely adjust my music (as in no looking at a screen(!)), I could reply "In class, talk later" to all of those pesky texts I would get mid-day. When the Time update came out, I could even make it vibrate on the hour, rather than beep! All of this in a small, lightweight package that took 2 hours to charge and lasted over a week per.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually whacked it too hard to get the display back, and it's never worked since. Initially it boot looped, now it's cold dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Android Wear&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it's 2016, and Pebble either doesn't exist or is in big trouble, I'm not sure which it was. I was in college, and the smartwatch was pretty much the thing that got me to class on time, since the calendar would buzz my wrist and snap me out of whatever it was I was doing. Obviously, I didn't want to just leave it at that, I wanted another smartwatch. Fortunately it broke between semesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been researching for a bit, keeping an eye on the market since I knew that the Pebble was having problems long before it actually died. So, after some consideration, I ordered an Asus ZenWatch 2. It wasn't fancy by any means, but it wasn't super expensive and seemed to have a good set of features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's just say it was fine, but I was pretty let down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, it has a touchscreen. Why is this a thing? The menu interface on the Pebble did all I wanted it to and then some, and I could reliably pause the music in the car with a button combo that stayed the same every time I used it. The touchscreen worked fine, but it wasn't &lt;em&gt;nearly&lt;/em&gt; as reliable, and it didn't actually provide a single benefit over the buttons on the Pebble. Sure, it's able to run a calculator app (which you have to &lt;em&gt;install&lt;/em&gt; from the Play Store) and it has a "functional" keyboard, but neither was really all that useful. Most of the &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; apps available for the watch used maybe two buttons, total. There'd be a left-side button and a right-side button, and that's it. Two of the swipe directions were used by the OS, too, so gestures were awkward at best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it lasted a day on charge, sometimes two if I was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; lucky. This isn't such a big deal, since I can't sleep with something on my wrist for some reason, so I would take it off anyhow and just plug it in overnight, but this severely limits my options when I'm camping, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also quite heavy. Generally, I believe a watch shouldn't be something that you &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; when you're going through your day. It's a simple tool that's there when you need to look at it, and simply invisible when you're not interested in the time. Plus, I use my left hand a lot, so it got caught on all sorts of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if all of that wasn't bad enough, it was tied to the &lt;em&gt;Google app&lt;/em&gt;. WTF!?!? What business does a timepiece (no matter how complicated) have with the Google app on my phone? I'm trying to get my calendar to buzz my wrist, not be able to do Google searches from there. I need my phone to do those anyhow, wouldn't it be much easier to use that? Or hey, I studied computer science, so I more often than not had a laptop on me, probably the single greatest portable research tool mankind has ever invented. Admittedly the watch would &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt; if I disabled/uninstalled the Google app, but Android Wear really didn't like it and would bug me to turn it back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function I probably thought was most clever from the Pebble was the vibrate-on-the-hour feature they had. I realize this was probably a case of necessity being the mother of invention, but it was wonderful to have that signal every hour so that I wouldn't become too hyper-focused and lose track of time. It was great not having to disturb people around me in the process. I could get an hourly beep on the ZenWatch, again with an app, but it wasn't super reliable. If I hadn't touched the watch in a while, the OS would suspend the beep app and it would miss an hour when it rolled over. To make matters even worse, the next time I would wake the watch the app would come back and beep. While it's good that it didn't beep over and over for every hour missed, just once, it was annoying having it beep at 12:37 instead of 11 and then 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could mention the fact that the vibration motor was weaker, or the fact that it has a microphone and speaker, or the insanely awkward gestures to change watch faces, or the health tracker I couldn't disable, but honestly those things didn't bother me as much. The health tracker part &lt;em&gt;should have&lt;/em&gt; in hindsight, but at the time it didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Moving On&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I switched to i3 from KDE on pretty much all of my computers at some point in there. What that meant was that I had an insane amount of control over parts of my workspace that I just plain didn't before. i3 is built for &lt;em&gt;power users&lt;/em&gt; and it makes you a power user if you try to use it for anything other than light computing. Did I mention I was studying computer science? Eventually, I integrated Calcurse into my status line. There's a neat feature of Calcurse where you can query it on the CLI and it will print out your next calendar event and how much time until it starts. Naturally, I started putting my class schedule in there, too, and then I added the text to my status line. I had it available at a glance. Eventually, I found that to be so much better of a tool for planning out what I was going to do each day that I started to become annoyed when my wrist would buzz for the next class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around this time that a friend of mine showed up with a new toy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1980's Smarty McSmartwatch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had bought a CA-53W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, it was perfect timing, too, since I had landed on my ZenWatch a couple of times while riding my skateboard, and it was in pretty rough shape. To be clear, it still works to this day, but there's a small crack in the top corner of the glass bezel, so it's not in perfect shape anymore. So, hearing it was only $15 rather than $150, and realizing that I was using it almost as much to lazily calculate tips at the local brewery as any other "smartwatch" feature, I opted to put the ZenWatch away and buy myself a Casio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opted to buy 3 of them, one F-91W (the cheap resin non-calculator watch), one A153W (the steel band version of the same, just in case I needed to look a little fancier), and the CA-53W. I daily drove that watch more or less until the pandemic hit. You would be surprised how nice they can be when you're working in embedded systems. I had to do conversions to and from hex for addressing and many other things, but if I wanted to calculate how much memory space I had to squeeze in another struct, my watch had my back and I didn't even have to reach across my desk for the desk calculator (by coincidence, also a Casio).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fit my needs almost perfectly, and there's still only one gripe I have with it to this day, and this applies to the others, it can't vibrate on the hour, only beep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pandemic and Beyond&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right before the pandemic hit, I bought another $10 watch. This time, it was an analog with a nylon weave strap. This one looked nicer (as if that was hard), and had all of the advantages of an analog watch in terms of gauging time relative to another time. It's like wearing a time pie chart. I wore this until it broke (maybe don't buy no-name with the intention of it lasting years?) and after that I started daily driving the A153W, since the steel is surprisingly sturdy, and I already have it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in a funny way, the advent of the smartwatch put an 80's designed digital watch on my wrist, and it's probably not going anywhere any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="electronics"></category><category term="style"></category><category term="theory"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>Fishing</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/fishing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-20T15:57:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-20T15:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2022-08-20:/fishing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's a time and a place for hard work, and there's a time and a place for just hanging out with friends and going fishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've heard a few people I know claim that they've never understood fishing, and they can't seem to fathom why anybody would do it. To …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's a time and a place for hard work, and there's a time and a place for just hanging out with friends and going fishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've heard a few people I know claim that they've never understood fishing, and they can't seem to fathom why anybody would do it. To them, it's a lot of nothing. In this post I'm stepping well outside my comfort zone and addressing why this person needs to go fishing most out of anybody in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Actual Work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious angle to take is that of tradesmanship. Learning to fish gives you a backup way to support yourself in almost any area that has a large enough body of water. Of course, this resource is not infinite, but it can be enough for a person to feed themselves in hard times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond this, though, there's a certain amount of patience and diligence that fishing will teach a person. It's not always easy to find the right spot to catch, and even if you do, fish are creatures too and can be just as wary of an ill-hooked worm as you would be. There are also just off days and spots where the fish don't like to hang around for one reason or another. There's nothing wrong with having a short patience, in many places fishing won't test it very much at all with the right combination of bait and available fish. Even this, however, can teach a person the value of attempting something they may not succeed at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;As recreation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a certain amount of connection that you can form with a person by fishing with them. Being patient with line and hook is a sign of a patient, collected person. When you hook a bush or snap your line, you open yourself up to the other person and show them who you are, too. Because it's a calm, relaxed setting, people will tend to let their guard down as they fish, and simply soak in the meditative atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more so, fishing is a low-stress activity, something that anybody of any age can enjoy. A six-year-old and a 96 year old can both sit at the same shore and connect as friends or family just by sitting and letting the time pass.*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a little patience, you'll succeed more than you fail. Maybe that's a metaphor for life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* As an aside, who doesn't like the look on a kid's face then they've just caught their first fish?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="Fising"></category><category term="outdoors"></category><category term="lifestyle"></category></entry><entry><title>Muscle over Motor: Why Biking is the Way to Travel the Last Mile</title><link href="https://cannoncontraption.github.io/biking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-04T16:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-04T16:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jim Read</name></author><id>tag:cannoncontraption.github.io,2022-08-04:/biking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In high school, I was the bike kid. I think every high school has at least one person like me, you know, that guy who rides a bike literally everywhere. In all honesty, looking back at it, I wouldn't shut up about it. The more time goes on, the more …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In high school, I was the bike kid. I think every high school has at least one person like me, you know, that guy who rides a bike literally everywhere. In all honesty, looking back at it, I wouldn't shut up about it. The more time goes on, the more I believe this is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;I Like Cars!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoa, whiplash anyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's true, though. I learned to drive a manual transmission at the same time as I learned to drive. It was very efficient! This gave me an immediate appreciation for driving, as anyone who drives a small stick shift car can tell you. There's a certain connection with the vehicle that isn't possible any other way. I currently drive a sporty little Mazda3, which is incredibly fun to take on backroads on the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even so, it's an expensive hobby, and not something I want to turn into a chore. I like driving, but I like it because it's fun, not because it's practical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;I Bike Everywhere I Practically Can.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live west of Boston. Anyone who knows this area probably thinks of winding, narrow roads surrounded by trees, punctuated by the occasional stroad or highway. That's about spot on. The amount of consideration bikes are given here is insanely low, this is the very type of situation I believe road design regulations were created to prevent, though in all reality those were created only considering cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that said, I don't feel unsafe on a bike. I'm sure this is different in the American south, and other places in the world that think of cyclists as opinionated, wimpy, avocado-toast-addicted morons, but in my corner of the world, people in cars are generally pretty courteous. They tend to give you space on the road, they watch carefully to keep from running into you, and they wait to pass you if there isn't enough space. That's not to say that nobody is crazy or entitled on the road, but so far my Close Call Counter is still in the single-digits since I started riding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I ride everywhere. If I'm low on milk or out of apples, I jump on my bike and ride to the store. If I need a new pair of jeans, I jump on my bike and ride to the local thrift store, or very rarely the local clothing store. There's a pharmacy within biking distance, all of downtown, a brewpub and coffee roaster, another brewpub, and a ton of other local business and restaurants. The vast, vast majority of things I do can be serviced by a bike. I even ride my bike to visit friends miles away. I ride everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why? You Just Said You Like Your Car...&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's true, I like my car, I love driving. In spite of this, I still bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, there's the cost equation. I remember actually running these numbers in high school when I was considering whether to buy a car. I was actually pretty amazed. The obvious two expenses are the cost of the vehicle and the cost of gas. These are the two things most people think about. However, when you take into account insurance, repair costs, oil, random filter changes, and so on, the cost per year is incredibly high. Even if your gas cost is somehow zero and you don't drive anywhere, you still need annual inspections from the state (at least here in MA), current insurance, registration, and a pile of other random fees. Even if your car is free, before you've driven a single mile, you've already paid more than you would need to buy a pretty nice bike, kitted out with headlights and taillights for nighttime riding, a rear rack for cargo, fenders for when it rains, and a new coat for riding in the winter. I could get rid of my car and buy a new, relatively high-end bike with the money I would save each year. I actually paid for my car and buy gas for it, so I could probably actually buy more like 2-3 bikes of the same variety as the one I own each year for the same cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think that's the end of the costs, you're mistaken. That's just what you pay for, and I didn't even mention everything. Do your own accounting and your picture will probably look pretty similar to mine, just make sure you count all the expenses you incur as a result of the car. There's more than just monetary costs, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also health implications to driving as well. Your tolerance for extreme heat and cold will be severely damaged, where riding a bike will acclimate you to even relatively extreme seasonal weather changes pretty painlessly and gradually (which will make the day the heat goes out way easier). You'll stay in shape better, you'll have more energy, you'll have less risk of injury from common tasks just due to your body adapting to doing even light work, and this in turn will lead to extra &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; on your life and a better attitude in the mean time. For those of you worried about COVID, this also does improve your immune response to viruses like COVID. That means less sick days lying in bed. That's not even mentioning the emissions from the cars that you aren't generating, making everyone else healthier. On top of all of this, the WHO recommends at least 30 minutes of moderate exercise in order to maintain a baseline of health, so you can think of your first half an hour of riding each day as essentially multitasking, you get that minimum benefit out of it. Anything in addition is like putting in a little extra time at the gym. You're unlikely to regret it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think those emissions are a serious risk to someone on a bike, you'll probably be interested to know that being in a car doesn't reduce your own risk at all. In fact, depending on where the air intake in your car is, you may actually be inhaling more toxic fumes from driving. This really is a wash either way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have the stats in front of me, but I hear anecdotally that a large proportion of bike accidents are due to biking drunk. If you don't, your risk of getting into an accident on your bike (involving a car or otherwise) should be pretty low, even compared to driving. My own experience is that while driving tired is incredibly dangerous, especially if my body is on the verge of sleep (very late at night), the added physical activity from biking keeps me alert enough that even at 2AM I'm not about to run into anything. Alertness is not a problem in the same way (though you NEED to equip your bike with BOTH front &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; back lights colored appropriately if you ride at night. &lt;strong&gt;DO NOT CHEAP OUT ON THIS, IT'S NOT WORTH THE $30 SAVINGS.&lt;/strong&gt; Plus, it's only like $30-$60, compare that to headlights and tail lights on a car.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me personally, I have a well-fitted bike with a rack and fenders, so I can haul almost two weeks of groceries in one trip, and that's with only some pretty basic pannier bags and no milk crate on top. Also, no bike trailer. These can be had cheaply on Craigslist or Ebay, not to mention new from most places that sell bike anything. You can haul a lot more than you might think on a bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;There Are Some Drawbacks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biking takes longer than driving. If your commute is 50+ miles, might I suggest moving closer to work? I bet you would save money even with a more expensive house. But, barring that, biking probably isn't practical over that distance every day. While safety isn't the big glaring concern you've probably been led to believe it is, you do still need to be aware that you're not in a giant metal box. Stay to the side of the road and keep your eyes up and open. Owning an upright bike helps with safety much more than even owning a helmet, so it's probably wise to choose your ride carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're also exposed to the elements. If it's hot, bring water. Bottle cages can be had for less than $10, bring water when it's over maybe 30-32 degrees C, (a little under 90F or so, if I recall). Wear a coat in winter. As much as this is a drawback, see my earlier section for why this is a benefit. If you're afraid of the cold, remember that you're doing work by riding, you'll stay surprisingly warm. After the first time or two overdressing, you'll know what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn't think of any more big drawbacks, at least none that I've run into. My bike doesn't have the same carrying capacity as my hatchback, but think around the same as a Mazda Miata. Anyone who's owned one of those knows how deceptive they are, you can really fit a lot more than you think in one. Bikes are kind of like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My bike is my vehicle of choice the vast majority of the time, and for most of you it probably should be, too. If you're not sold, do your own research, buy a bike, and try it. Even if you use it part of the year, having it around the next time gas prices go crazy will be a huge help. I haven't even really talked about bikes as recreation, you probably already know about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in conclusion, ride a bike! I'll see you out there!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="travel"></category><category term="car"></category><category term="bike"></category><category term="commute"></category></entry></feed>